hello laser and holography Enthusiast
and welcome to another week of holotalk
this is a special broadcast this week in
fact we have a special guest Todd Stark
who is director of programs and Exhibits
for the Discovery Center of Science and
Technology in Bethlehem Pennsylvania and
as you may recall if you've listened to
our shows in the past you know for
probably six or eight weeks now we've
been talking about a traveling exhibit
of lasers and Holograms it's coming to
the Lehigh Valley area that's been put
together by this Science Center and
we're going to host it at the Discovery
Center of Science and Technology while
Todd took some time to come into the
studio this week and sit down so that
the whole talk listeners can get
first-hand information and some detailed
information on what this exhibit is all
about one of the things that we did not
touch on and I promised Todd I would
mention is there's going to be a smaller
exhibit that goes along with this
there's a few students in the Lehigh
Valley who receive the grant to put
together a Star Trek exhibit on where
lasers and Holograms will be in the 24th
century sort of a futuristic look at
lasers and Holograms and I just want to
let you know that that's going to be
included also in the exhibit
would come out to see the main exhibit
and I had a chance to see the model this
week from one of the students they put a
model together when they applied for the
grant and it's very nice it's a very
nice little exhibit that you're going to
put together so don't forget to check
out the Star Trek laser and hologram
exhibit that runs along with this if you
come out to the Discovery Center
excuse me so as far as details Todd's
going to fill us in on that and there's
also a link on the Holo talk page where
you can
click on that link and there's a page at
the web exam that I put up today to show
you a few pictures that were sent out in
the press kit and also give you some
more information and you can get on a
mailing list
for email list every so often we'll send
out some information and perhaps there's
special programs that we're going to run
or
maybe even a special side exhibit of
amateur and hobbyist Holograms and
there's a lot of things that can take
place between now and when this opens in
June so if you want to have all the
latest information just click on the
link on the laser and hologram page
and every so often you'll receive an
email which will give you updated
information on what's Happening so let's
move on to the interview with Todd Stark
I'm not going to come back on at the end
so let me at this time say thank you for
tuning in and here's the interview with
Todd Stark
okay we're in the studio uh with Todd
Stark who is the director of programs
and exhibits at the Discovery Center of
science and technology which is in
Bethlehem Pennsylvania Todd I want to
welcome the whole talk well welcome
thank you uh Frank thanks for having me
um we're going to be talking about the
new exhibit that's coming into the area
and it's very exciting if you may
remember we had an exhibit that traveled
through this uh what we call the
Northeast Corridor
um
probably a few years ago at the Franklin
Institute of Philadelphia which was
lasers Holograms and virtual reality and
since then we've been in a quite a bit
of a dry spell
and it's a wonderful opportunity for
everyone in this area to come out and
finally have another major exhibit of
lasers and Holograms in this area now I
know you were involved with Cosi which
was the touring company behind what the
exhibit was in Philadelphia is there
some comparisons things that are the
same things that are different that
maybe let some of the listeners know
about sure
um well liquid Vision which was the uh
the official name of that exhibit that
was traveled in Franklin was there about
three and a half years ago on its
opening tour and
um
it was it's very much centered around
the high-tech industry and oh by the way
had Holograms that it showed it had a
really nice collection of holograms uh
and that this exhibit here lasers and
Holograms uh traveled by the Pacific
Science Center out of Seattle Washington
uh focuses more on getting to understand
how Holograms are created what you can
do with Holograms
um what their interactions are with
lasers the importance of lasers in our
lives how they work how to do laser
shows and that
um so in the area of lasers and
Holograms this exhibit here is much more
interactive than the liquid Vision
exhibition which tended to stray more
toward the the three-dimensional
computer graphics and high-tech Glitz
and and that but dealt very little with
the actual Holograms themselves from
what I've been able to see with the the
promotional materials that I've had it
seems to me that the is happening at
just the right time some of the past
hologram exhibits that had traveled
around such as the one in Philadelphia
and also images and time and space which
did its round in Canada and out on the
west coast was more of a wow look at
this type of an exhibit now I think
we're moving beyond that and we're
saying okay we've been wowed tell us how
is this going to affect our lives how is
this going to affect our children's
decision as far as career someday can my
child go out and actually support a
family or whatever it is that they want
to do in these fields and I think that's
where we're moving at and and this is
definitely one of the focal points of
this exhibit which is called by the way
lasers and Holograms exploring the
splendid light and it's a touring
exhibit by Pacific Science Center
and do you want to take a few moments
and do you have an idea of what some of
these little interactive exhibits are
that the people okay tell us a little
bit if someone were to come out and I
guess I could spend quite a bit of time
going around each and every little
station but what are some of the
highlights that they can expect to see
if they come out to the Discovery Center
right well you know I happen to agree
with you uh Frank on on the wow factor
for Holograms I think is past uh you
know since we're finding holograms on
our driver's licenses and uh credit
cards and that
um there are more and more applications
for lasers and Holograms um
you know we there's going to be I think
there's over 18 large-scale Holograms
very impressive
um pictures
um some from holographics North to
um private producers and that uh in
there but that's not the focus that's
not the feature of it it's it's sort of
complementary to the exhibits and
Hands-On activities that we've got going
on there with this exhibit uh we look
into the world of fiber optics you know
lasers and Holograms are linked of
course really closely and fiber optics
is the next step in in
telecommunications
um it's it's most of what's carrying the
net as it is now but very few people
have a true understanding of what fiber
optics is in that it has a huge display
on a very large scale fiber optic piece
allows you to look through it as if you
were looking through that glass rod
um if you were a light beam uh going
through it
um they've got a little uh kiosk that
allows you to mix your own little laser
light show of course you know lasers
aren't just professional use but for
entertainment value as well
um they have
in the areas of holograms they talk
about
um what what the fraction uh gradings
and diffraction uh images are and
interference patterns
um how they're creating how that helps
create the illusion of a hologram
um they've got other exhibits that uh
let's see that deal with um everyday
applications you know lasers and CDs and
writable and readable CD-ROMs things
that are happening in the background
that you don't see is happening with
lasers right in your own home exactly
um one of the other exhibits that had
traveled with it but for technical
difficulties and there was a barcode
reader from a supermarket okay and then
another application of lasers so the
kids are really going to get in and
interact with several different smaller
scale components dealing with different
facets of of lasers and applications of
lasers and their everyday lives and the
creation of holograms they have a
holographic table that allows you to
literally trace a actual laser beam
throughout it I see in the making of a
hologram in the making of a hologram you
can look through it and see the Hologram
image being made on the plate
um they've got another one where you can
study the
um
uh study how lasers are used to test and
measure things uh they've got a steel
plate the laser beam goes out and if you
press on the plate you can actually see
it the calibration change oh that's the
interferometer yeah thank you that yes
and that's covered as well so there's a
lot of great little application it's
going to be a really fun glitzy uh
exhibit and we hope to complement it
with some some wonderful program
programmatic aspects that we'll be
developing over the next couple months
maybe maybe we should touch a little bit
on what information you have now about
some of the educational programs that
will be available
uh the Discovery Center of science and
technology is is very dedicated in not
just having students come in and see
science but experience it and show them
how they can move on later in their life
as far as career decisions and I
understand you're going to be running a
series of summer programs that will
center right around careers of Science
and Technology and will also include the
careers of lasers and Holograms during
that week could you tell us a little
about that that is correct uh we're
running of course our week-long summer
camp as many institutions like ourselves
do throughout the country this year
we're focusing on
um become a scientist for a day and
we've picked several different
scientists careers uh biologists uh
chemists zoologists uh geologists
of course a laser holographers
um computer Specialists and we want to
explore explore those through wonderful
Hands-On interactive activities uh
experiments games throughout the week
we're kind of devoting half days to a
theory the number of different careers
and it's sort of just to get the kids
what their appetites into you know if I
want to grow up and I want to be a
scientist what kind of cool things can I
get involved in uh and as you said
lasers and Holograms is going to be
featured during part of that day and
hopefully the kids will get a better
understanding of what it takes to make a
laser and or take to make a hologram
um you know what kind of things how can
they make money you know using lasers
and stuff that they think that's really
cool uh so exploring those Avenues with
our uh six to 12 year olds is where
we're headed with that okay
um I'd also like to point out to people
that some of the Holograms that are
going to be on exhibit Believe It or Not
didn't start out as just Holograms but
began during the photographic process
with traditional photography which are
called holographic stereograms so if
you're a photographer or part of a 3D
stereo Group which seemed to be cropping
up and becoming a very popular lately
you definitely want to stop over to the
Discovery Center and see some of these
because some of these Holograms
originally started with a photographic
process not just holographic
a series of photographs are taken from
different perspectives and then those
photographs are processed in the
traditional manner as some actually are
used with digital technology but they're
then brought into the laboratory and all
those different perspectives
perspectives are actually digitized and
brought into the holographic process
where you have a three-dimensional
hologram is the final product so this is
not that far away from I know we have a
lot of Photography clubs and amateur
amateur photographers out there I'm sure
that you would be absolutely thrilled to
see what's possible to do with your own
camera and then have those pictures made
into a three-dimensional hologram
um the dates would you like to tell us
about dates and times and hours of
operation how we can get in touch with
you if you want some more information I
I know we're going to put some
information on the web there's going to
be some information right at the web
Zoom for everybody coming through and
the Discovery Center also has uh
his site so Todd why don't you fill us
in on how we can get more information on
this sure
um the lasers and Holograms exhibition
will be running this summer it will open
up on Saturday June 6th uh to the
general public and we'll run all the way
through September uh Sunday September
13th so I'll be here all summer your
chance to check it out
um you'll be you can catch us at the
Discovery Center uh Tuesdays through
Saturdays uh 9 30 to 4 30 and Sunday is
12 30 to uh 4 30.
um
we're very reasonably priced uh in the
center of the valley of course we've got
the regular Discovery Center uh exhibits
and
um you can get any adult prices 450.
kids under 12 or 350 and children three
and under are free
the lasers and Holograms exhibition will
cost just an extra dollar fifty per
person and of course while you're there
you can also check out our laser show
that we're producing
um this year we've managed to uh through
a funding source get some upgrade and
some equipment allows us to do some
animated
um programs so we're going to be doing a
laser light show we're producing it
right now
um as a amateur laser show producer this
is uh come in quite a learning
experience I've seen some of this stuff
it's pretty cool yeah it is pretty cool
and it is amazing what they're able to
do now uh nowadays we'll be telling the
story of how laser shows are are made
through the actual laser show itself and
there you go there's a unique use uh
educational we're not just doing its
rock music just Pink Floyd people no
it's not with a learning experience and
be entertained at the same time and
that's what we're trying to do with it
okay I was going to give you a laser
what I want to let people know and I
don't know if they know this or not but
believe it or not if you live in the New
York Philadelphia Baltimore Washington
DC Corridor you can get to the Discovery
Center of Science and Technology without
even experiencing a red light until
you're only several blocks away from the
actual Center of course you would get on
95 north and we'll have some specific
directions for you but I know a lot of
times
with Summer traffic construction all
these other things and people just say
look this trip is just too long you know
don't worry about it once you're on 95
unless you want to stop to grab
something to eat or you choose to stop
you will not even experience a red light
until you want about three blocks away
from the center that's just about right
so it's almost door-to-door so no excuse
if you live far away jump in the car and
come on up the laser light show is is
but we we had a laser light show there
it was uh
a laser light show that uh I guess low
scale is a good word for I without I
can't think of the term but it produced
all those little luxurious patterns and
whatever and L Michael Roberts is
actually going to be a guest on the show
so he'll probably be able to tell us
what these things mean in a couple weeks
but the laser lights show that they have
now is a professional system that's done
through a computer system and runs very
high speed scanners
and is capable of drawing out animations
and words telling stories and it's all
part of your experience when you come to
the Discovery Center and like we said
before it's not just an entertainment
experience but you learn something
believe it or not a lot of times you go
out in the car and you hit yourself in
your head and you didn't even realize
you learned it and you did you did so
any closing remarks you'd like to make
to uh the whole talk listeners before we
head out here well I think uh for any of
the uh hologram enthusiasts I think a
trip to the Discovery Center uh to see
this collection of holograms and
hopefully complemented by some other
amateur uh holography amateur and
professional Holograms that we'll
hopefully have there uh we'll make a
very rewarding and very worthwhile
experience for anyone that is in the
holograph uh holography business or
holography interests and and lasers and
that and uh you know the Discovery
Center is not just for kids it's for
kids of all ages um anyone's a kid that
heart and loves to learn and loves to
look at Wild Cool meat stuff and
actually learn a little something along
the way okay and before I say goodbye to
Todd I'm going to add one more thing to
this and that I hear a lot of times
emails from people what's happening with
holography where can I see Holograms
there's nothing happening in the area
with Holograms here's your opportunity
who knows when it's going to happen
again so if you don't come up and see
this show don't send me any emails
whining about the fact that you can't
see any Holograms anymore because I I'm
just going to delete them I'm not going
to even answer them now's your
opportunity if you don't take advantage
of it shame on you so Todd thank you
very much for being with me and we look
forward to this and personally a thank
you from me for giving lasers and
Holograms an opportunity to come into
the area for people to experience it and
thank you from the whole talk listeners
as well take care thank you